Previously...
We've come to arrest her
for the murder of Malva Christie.
Let them both be taken, if you will.
I will travel with them.
Hang her!
This isn't justice!
I want to spend my time
with you and Jemmy,
just the three of us.
Well, the four of us.
Really?
- Jamie!
- Claire!
Where are you taking Jamie?
That's none of your concern.
What if I want to make
the preaching official?
I heard there's a Presbytery in Edenton.
We'll start packing tomorrow
and leave as soon as we can.
Your husband is alive.
Trust in God.
He will deliver the righteous
out of danger.
You think I'm righteous?
I will not leave town.
Uncle Jamie?
I canna let
my darkest fears cripple me.
Blood of my blood, bone of my bone,
I gave ye my spirit
till our life shall be done.
And that's why I ken ye're alive still.
I'd feel it if you were gone.
You live.
I ken it in my bones, and I will find you.
Horses are watered, Uncle Jamie.
John Quincy and the Cherokee
are away back to the Ridge
to see that all is well, just as ye asked.
And ye're right.
We'll attract less attention
in town this way.
Uncle Jamie?
Let's go get my wife.
♪ Sing me a song ♪
♪ Of a lass that is gone ♪
♪ Say, could that lass ♪
♪ Be I? ♪
♪ Merry of soul ♪
♪ She sailed on a day ♪
♪ Over the sea ♪
♪ To Skye ♪
♪ Billow and breeze ♪
♪ Islands and seas ♪
♪ Mountains of rain and sun ♪
♪ All that was good ♪
♪ All that was fair ♪
♪ All that was me ♪
♪ Is gone ♪
♪ Sing me a song ♪
♪ Of a lass that is gone ♪
♪ Say, could that lass ♪
♪ Be I? ♪
♪ Merry of soul ♪
♪ She sailed on a day ♪
♪ Over the sea ♪
♪ To Skye ♪
♪ Sing me a song ♪
♪ Of a lass that is gone ♪
♪ Say, could that lass ♪
♪ Be I? ♪
Sorry. I- I didn't mean to disturb you.
Think nothing of it.
Did he give you money?
Yes, a bit.
Well, call the old bizzom
and send for some Holland, why don't you?
Who?
Mrs. Tolliver?
Mrs. Tolliver!
Really, Mrs. Ferguson,
you are the most dreadful nuisance.
I was just coming to pay my respects
to Mrs. Fraser in any case.
Mrs. Fraser, I am Mrs. Tolliver.
- Mrs. Tolliver.
- I'm to see to your welfare
and acquaint you with our custom.
You will receive one meal each day,
unless you wish to send
to the ordinary for more,
at your own expense.
I will bring a basin
for washing once a day,
and you will carry your own slops.
Stuff your custom, Maisie.
She has some money.
Fetch us a bottle of geneva.
There's a good girl.
Then if you must,
you can tell her what's what.
A shilling, then.
You've missed supper,
but as you've just come,
I'll make an allowance
and bring you something.
Thank you. I'm famished.
None for me, thanks.
Just the gin.
Please, could you get a word to my family?
That I cannot do. I'm sorry.
Fraser, she said.
You aren't the, uh...
...murderess?
I don't want to talk about it.
As you like.
Welcome to your new home, then.
Used to be a slaughterhouse, they say.
Seems about right.
It's grand here, it is.
Sit, sit.
You must be bone tired.
I'm Sadie, by the bye.
- Claire.
- You, uh...
any good at cards, Claire?
Know a game called Brag?
Let me guess.
You're in here for cheating at cards.
Cheat?
Sadie Ferguson?
Not a bit of it.
Forgery.
All right then, but not for money.
Hmm.
We'll play for beans then, shall we?
How long have you been in here?
A month, almost.
29 days, by last count.
You haven't had a trial yet?
No, praise God.
Hasn't been anybody
tried in the last two months.
Maisie says the court's shut down,
all the justices gone into hiding.
So here too, then?
Well, I wouldn't be
in a hurry, dearie.
If they've not tried you,
they can't hang you.
- I am innocent.
- 'Course you are.
You stick to it.
Don't let 'em bully-whack you
into admitting
the least little thing.
I won't.
But I don't want to languish
here in jail either.
If the courts aren't open now--
One who should worry about
hanging's the sheriff.
What I hear, a mob's liable to come here
and string him up if he don't look sharp.
There's unrest in the streets,
if you hadn't noticed.
The rebels have made it hell
for any loyal subject.
What ails you, Mistress?
I could not tell her what it was.
Could not say that I knew
just how long this war would last,
that the courts would likely remain closed
for years to come,
and we would languish here without rescue.
It feels like I'm throwing you
to the wolves.
I think they're more commonly
known as wives.
Same difference.
Are you gonna be okay
with Reverend McMillan?
Surely I can handle ministering
to a few soldiers.
I'm a veteran myself now, sort of.
And I'm tough.
I had my wayward youth.
Smoking, drinking beer.
Wow.
Stealing sweeties from the post office.
Quite the wee criminal for a while.
The terror of Inverness.
Son of a preacher man.
Still, I think Reverend McMillan wants
to test my mettle,
make sure I'm not too focused
on the lofty, intellectual
parts of my studies.
What is it?
There's something written
all over your face.
What do you even say to a preacher?
"Break a leg" doesn't seem right.
"God luck"?
Good day to you both.
Thank you, Mistress MacKenzie,
for your willingness to assist
with the almsgiving,
especially since you'll only be
with us for a few weeks.
Of course.
Are you ready, Mr. MacKenzie?
The soldiers we'll encounter today
are mustering to go north.
Now, it's not for us to judge
which side they have chosen to fight for,
but know that they'll be
in need of much prayer
and supplication.
Good day, young one.
Could we offer you some comfort
through the word of God?
The future Reverend MacKenzie
was at the Battle of Alamance.
Doin' what, exactly?
Carryin' the white flag of surrender?
Bible verse ain't gonna help us.
Knowin' how to wield a knife,
use our fists, maybe.
There's nothin'
in your holy book about that.
What advice can these
devil-dodgers give us, eh?
"Float like a butterfly.
Sting like a bee."
And God will surely go with thee.
Ali.
What did you just say?
Muhammad Ali.
You're a traveler, aren't you, like me?
You gotta help me.
Who are you?
Wendigo Donner.
You were one of Lionel Brown's men.
Claire Fraser told me--
I didn't do nothing to her, okay?
I swear.
I was gonna help her get away.
Didn't she tell you?
Why would I hurt her?
She's like us, isn't she?
I was conscripted from jail,
but I'm not a thief, okay?
I just needed a gemstone
to get back to my own time.
I've still got it, but I'm stuck here.
I came back to help
the Indian Nations, but...
Well, Claire did tell me that.
The plan just got all screwed up.
Five of us made it
to the stones at Ocracoke,
but we got split up when we went through.
I don't know what happened.
I never saw them again.
I never even made it
to where I was supposed to go.
Look, I don't wanna hurt anybody.
I just wanna go home.
You get that, right?
Please... help me.
Sun's barely up,
and look at the state of Tolly,
while we're here slaving away
at the arse-crack of dawn.
Well, she's breathing fine,
though a glass of water wouldn't hurt.
I doubt she'd drink it
if there's no gin in it.
Open it.
Ye gods and little fishes.
Here we are, Margit.
Who's this now?
Which is the healer?
That would be me.
What is she charged with?
Well, one of 'em's a forger,
a few of them are thieves,
and one of them's a murderess.
Fletcher, Ferguson-- somethin' like that.
But as to which one being which...
You mean to say you don't know?
I'm paid to guard 'em,
not hobnob with 'em.
- I'm the murderess.
- Sadie.
Very well.
Come with me.
Well, where are we going?
I'm afraid we're in a hurry, madam.
Mr. Christie!
I'm glad to see ye kept yer word.
- Where is Claire?
- She's gone.
You were supposed to keep watch!
The guards wouldn't allow me
to stand out here all night.
When I came back this morning,
it was already too late.
I did everything in my power.
The sheriff assured me
they'd treat her with dignity.
They're saying
that Auntie Claire was taken.
Was it that bastard, Brown?
No, no, it was soldiers
looking for a healer.
Where was she taken?
They couldna tell me.
Could not or would not?
Got any drink, have you, sir?
Or a few bob to pay for some?
Drop of something for my poor old throat.
Tell me what you know.
A shilling more and we'll make it
a wee dram or two instead, shall we?
Nice lady.
Did my best to help her.
If anything, you probably ought
to be thanking me.
If you truly want to help,
then tell me what you know, please.
She told 'em your wife was a forger
and tried to claim
the murder charge for herself.
Oh, no pardon possible for forgery.
Capital crime.
But as for murder,
she probably thinks
she can plead the Good Book,
repent for her sins,
and get off scot-free.
Don't be daft.
You're living in fairy world
if you think I'd get away with that.
I was trying to help her.
Enough.
You'd better thank the Lord
that that guard is watching.
Now tell me! Where did they take my wife?
How the bleedin' hell should I know?
It's Tolly you want to ask.
Mrs. Tolliver's the sheriff's wife.
She was as drunk as a lord
when those men came.
I'm not even sure both
of 'em were soldiers as such.
What did they look like, these men?
How would I know?
They all look the same to me.
What's going on here?
Are you Mrs. Tolliver?
I'm James Fraser.
I demand to know where my wife was taken.
All I know is she was taken
on my husband's orders.
A matter of duty to the Crown.
And where is he, your husband?
Do you think I'm privy to such information,
merely his wife?
He'd gone to quell some unrest,
rebels passing through
on their way to take Fort Johnston.
He's likely drinking
his own sorrows away by now.
Please go!
Come in.
Who the devil is this?
Healer, ma'am. Midwife.
A Mistress Fraser.
I'm told there's not
a single midwife to be found
in the entire county.
Where did you find her?
The workhouse or the local jail?
Jail, actually.
But, uh, since the ship's surgeon
is apparently in Fort Johnston
tending soldiers,
I'm afraid you're stuck with me.
God.
We're not that desperate yet, are we?
Plucked from a jail.
Imagine a governor driven
out of his palace
and forced to flee for his life.
My husband hunted
by mobs of his own citizens.
Marooned on this blasted ship
when everything's going to hell.
I'm sorry we're not meeting
under better circumstances.
But since your husband did send for me...
may I examine you?
I can help. I promise.
Have you been experiencing
any cramping, bleeding,
intermittent pain in your back?
No.
And how long have you been ill?
I've been vomiting all night
and sweated through the sheets.
Oh, I look positively ghastly.
Perhaps I'll take one of my tonics.
Are you taking all of these
tonics at once, Mrs. Martin?
One at breakfast,
another after luncheon.
When the fever comes on,
I use the East Indian Chaulmoogra.
Perhaps we can find you
something more suitable.
What if it's the tertian ague?
It's not.
Shouldn't you be letting my blood?
There's a fleam and bowl over there.
Unless...
Oh, God, is it true?
Are you the one who...
who murdered her husband's
pregnant mistress
and cut the baby from her womb?
It was you, wasn't it?
She was not his mistress.
And I didn't kill her.
As for the rest...
My husband doesn't know, does he?
I doubt it.
How did you hear?
Oh, you are quite notorious.
The talk of the town.
Of course, my husband has
no time for gossip
and has no memory for names, as I do.
I've never known a murderess before.
I'm not a murderess.
Well, of course, you'd say so.
You don't look depraved.
Though I must say, you don't
look quite respectable either.
It's ginger tea.
It will help with the nausea.
Not until you swear
you won't hurt my baby.
You must swear it.
Mrs. Martin... of course.
Your husband brought me here
because I'm a healer.
Harming someone would be rather
at cross purposes with that, wouldn't it?
You need fluids,
for your own sake and for the baby.
Six children I've had,
and I've lost three of them.
I'd rather die than lose another
and break my husband's heart.
He won't bear it.
You're in no danger of that.
I'd say you've eaten something
that strongly disagrees with you.
That's all.
I am a mother too.
Let's settle you into your cabin.
And I'll go ask your husband
to send for some different medicine.
Thank you.
I won't say anything
about the charge if you don't.
Right.
I'll see you later then.
Bye.
Whoa, what's all this?
Gosh, there's enough food
in here to last three days.
Are you leaving me?
It's nothing. Snacks.
And a farrier's hammer?
You're going back to hand out
theological pamphlets.
I didn't realize shoeing horses
was part of the job description.
Ministering to animals now as well?
That's for Wendigo Donner, isn't it?
You're gonna try to help him escape?
Roger, what are you gonna do?
Singlehandedly bust him out of the army?
Shh...
You're not Steve McQueen
in The Great Escape.
You're studying to be
a minister, for God's sake!
I know that.
I just...
I thought maybe I would put in
a good word for him
with the officers or... something.
- After what he did?
- Oh, but that's just it.
According to Claire,
he didn't do anything.
Right.
He just stood by and did nothing
while my mother was brutally attacked.
And then he ran and hid like a coward.
What could he have done without
getting killed himself?
You--you didn't see him, Bree.
He--he's desperate, scared.
He just wants to go home.
He--he came back here
to help his fellow Indians,
and everything went to shit.
He was just trying to survive.
When I came through the stones,
I ended up on Bonnet's crew.
I did what I had to.
And I would've done anything to find you.
Anything.
No. No.
You would never, ever stand by
and watch a woman be hurt,
not like those men did
in that tavern that night
when I came back,
and not like Wendigo did with Mama.
I watched Bonnet...
throw a child overboard on that ship...
...and her mother jump in after her.
And though I was desperate
to intervene, I was frozen.
I wanted to save them, but I couldn't.
I had to fight every instinct in me,
because I had to stay alive to find you.
I was outnumbered.
Bonnet and his crew would have killed me.
And it was the same for Wendigo.
So how can I condemn him,
as a man or as a minister?
- Yeah, Roger...
- Bree.
We'll be ready, Lieutenant Tate.
Catch a steady wind.
Go up the Cape Fear a bit.
Send raiding parties to shore,
and take back Fort Johnston.
With respect, Your Excellency,
if I may speak frankly,
you can't mean to try
and attack in this fog.
This is hardly the ship for it.
- And the Captain says--
- We have to do something, Tate.
Do you have any idea what fate awaits me
if I lose this wretched colony?
The Redcoats will hang me
before the goddamned rebels do.
We should have news imminently.
But the rebels are far more numerous
and better armed than expected.
And if they are holding
Fort Johnston, sir,
then for your own sake
and the sake of your family,
perhaps you might consider sailing north.
Forgive me...
...but surely, your place
is here, Governor Martin.
And yours, madam,
is in the surgeon's cabin,
tending to my wife.
Well, her condition is much improved.
I wanted to ask if I could go fetch
some additional supplies
in Wilmington for her.
Leave the ship?
Do you have any idea
what it took to bring you here?
Absolutely not.
But your wife's continued
good health may depend on it.
Ahoy there.
We're coming aboard,
by your leave,
in the name of King George's Army.
Please, Your Excellency,
I...
I just need to get some extra supplies.
Make a list, and we'll send a messenger
to collect whatever it is
you need before we set sail.
Be quick about it.
I don't imagine we'll be
in these waters much longer,
no matter what happens.
But when can I expect to return to shore?
It can't have escaped your notice
that my wife is with child.
She'll require your assistance.
You will remain on the ship
for the duration of our voyage.
Consider it your patriotic duty.
Lieutenant Tate will convey
your letter to shore at once.
Won't take long.
What news, Major MacDonald?
We've lost Fort Johnston, sir.
It's certain, then?
Fancy meeting you here.
You know her?
We've met.
We most certainly have.
Although last I heard,
- you were--
- Fully intent
on proving my innocence.
Thank you, Major.
Well, before
you two become reacquainted,
once you've given your letter to Tate,
could you fetch me something
to ease the griping in my stomach?
A splash of brandy in it
couldn't hurt either.
Redcoats in the whorehouse.
We might be able to get
something out of them.
Aye.
They might know where the sheriff is
or where he's taken Auntie Claire.
We can rally
Loyalists, find more troops.
Your servant, madam.
I couldn't quite believe
my ears when I heard
that you'd been arrested for murder...
...and- and that the girl's
father had accompanied you
to Wilmington with the express wish
of seeing you hanged.
He only wished to ensure
that I received a fair trial.
Of course.
If you're here
in such illustrious company,
then I- I'm sure
that all must be in order.
I assume this means that
your husband has seen sense
and finally declared himself
for the Crown, Mrs. Fraser?
You doubt this man's allegiance, Major?
Well, it's only that I assumed,
since the good lady's husband
resigned from his position
as Indian agent,
among other things, that they, uh...
How to put this politely...
Your husband is James Fraser
of Fraser's Ridge?
Yes. Yes, he is.
I do, of course,
very much hope
that we can count on
Mr. Fraser's support in our endeavors,
but there is some doubt,
certainly, as to the Frasers' integrity,
- as you can see.
- How dare you.
Could you excuse us, Major?
Certainly, your Excellency.
Manipulative bastard.
- Mr. Thomas Christie?
- Yes?
A Mistress Claire Fraser
requires your immediate
and most urgent assistance.
She has assured us that you
are the man best able to help.
But we require your utmost discretion.
You can procure the necessary items,
Mr. Christie?
Items?
Yes, of course.
Of course, yes.
For her patient aboard HMS Cruizer.
I am--I'm very happy to be of service
both to Mistress Fraser
and to the Crown.
And you will see that she has enclosed
a list of what is needed.
Now, please bring everything to the harbor
at your earliest convenience.
The ship, it's in the harbor?
No, sir.
But I will wait for you there
and convey whatever you bring,
by boat, back to the ship.
But please hurry.
The Cruizer will not be
at anchor for long.
Vir meus...
Sheriff Tolliver
orchestrated my being here,
so I assumed you knew what my charge was
and you were turning a blind eye.
Mistress Martin certainly did.
There is that rather insignificant matter
of trying to govern a royal colony
from a goddamned floating dungeon
that's been occupying my time.
The crew told me you were
a healer coming from the jail.
I had neither the time nor inclination
to ask for any of the unsavory details.
Exactly my point.
You didn't care what I'd done
when you sent for me.
You needed my help, and I gave it.
But a murderess, it's unthinkable.
I swear to you, I'm innocent.
I found the young woman
in question already dead.
But she was with child, so I--
God in heaven, it gets worse and worse.
My poor wife, does she know
about all of this sorry tale?
You don't understand.
I did what I could to save
that unborn child.
And I will do everything I can
for your wife and your baby.
Your wife told me
that you'd both suffered terrible losses.
I know what it's like to lose a child.
There is no greater pain.
It's unspeakable.
My three beautiful boys.
Sam, my youngest...
Sometimes I think I glimpse him
running past.
He was only eight years old.
I'm so sorry.
Yes, perhaps you should be,
you and your husband both,
because the only thing more
painful than losing my sons
is knowing that
my three daughters will grow up
in a world that exists without them,
without the men they would have become,
men who would have protected them
from those who choose violence
and bloodshed,
chaos and anarchy over law and order,
those who would betray
their nation and choose war.
But surely, no one enters war willingly,
no matter one's personal convictions.
And what exactly are you
and your husband's convictions,
Mistress Fraser?
To be charged with murder is one thing,
but to be suspected of treason
is quite another.
That was disappointing.
Maybe we'll have better luck
at the Old Bell.
Mr. Fraser.
What is it now, Mr. Christie?
I know where Mistress Fraser is.
Read it.
She's on a ship, the Cruizer.
She wants you to go to her.
Vir meus, my husband.
She wants you.
Lieutenant Tate.
Back down below, please, madam.
I just need some extra blankets
for Mrs. Martin.
Boat, ahoy!
Do you wish to come aboard, sir?
Aye, I do.
By whose authority?
I am a former Indian agent
in the governor's employ
and an acquaintance...
...of Lord John Grey.
Sassenach.
Excuse me.
This is not permitted.
I wish to speak with the governor.
I'm James Fraser of Fraser's Ridge.
I've come for my wife.
I humbly ask that you allow me
to take her home.
I regret to inform you, sir,
that your wife is a prisoner of the Crown,
though perhaps you were aware of this.
It is true, is it not,
that you have declared
martial law over the colony
of North Carolina?
It is.
Then you alone have control
over the custody of any prisoners.
My wife is in your custody.
You have the power to release her.
The crime of which
your wife stands accused
is most heinous.
There is no merit to the charge.
Surely, having made her acquaintance,
you'll have drawn your own conclusions
as to her character.
And what conclusions should I draw
as to your character?
Lord John Grey assured me
that you were a man to be counted upon,
- but Major MacDonald said--
- Major MacDonald?
My resignation as Indian agent?
Surely, that is all behind us.
Your unwillingness to elaborate
further on the matter
speaks volumes, sir.
I understand
Your Excellency's reservations.
Perhaps some surety may be offered.
You have the impertinence
to try and bribe me?
That was not my intent, sir.
What I offer is a bond against
my wife's appearance in court.
No, sir, I will not accept
a bond for your wife.
I should hang the two of you out of hand,
have you swinging from the yardarm.
Your Excellency, please.
I'm a reasonable man.
I will offer you a proposition.
Return to the backcountry
and gather such men as you can.
Then report to Major MacDonald
and commit your troops to his campaign.
When I receive word from him
that you have, say, 200 men,
then, sir, I will release
your wife to you.
Very well.
Be still, a nighean.
Do not despair.
I will see you when the morning comes.
Excuse me, Miss.
Do you have a moment to talk
about someone who loves you very much?
I don't have time to talk about God today.
Thanks anyway.
I was talking about your husband.
Do you have any time for him?
Always.
But he's been kinda busy
ministering to some soldiers.
He's going to be ordained
himself, you see.
- Oh?
- Mm.
And how is that going for him?
You'll be pleased to know
that he hasn't helped
a certain conscript escape.
But I do want to do something
for him, Bree.
You listen to your instincts.
I have to be able to listen to mine.
So I'm going to help Wendigo...
by praying for him.
Go on, then.
Do it now if it'll make you feel better.
Lord, it is said that God helps those
who help themselves.
I always found that confusing.
Like those who help themselves
to the last slice of cake,
or...
Lord, please help Wendigo Donner,
or at least help him to help himself.
You're going to be a great minister.
You'll never be able
to recruit enough men.
I willna be recruitin' men.
But I am goin' back to that ship.
What will you do, Uncle?
Whatever I must.
You should go back to the Ridge.
I dinna want ye involved.
What d'ye mean?
Fraser.
Tom.
Is that a whisky in yer hand?
I have wrestled with my demons.
But it's you.
It's always you.
You are the answer to my prayer.
How much have ye had to drink?
You must help me.
I beg you.
There is something I must do.
Some air to clear yer heid.
Ye're not accustomed to it.
Whisky's addled yer wits.
Over the years,
I've watched men come to you
and ask for your help.
You never turn them away.
Will you refuse me now?
Let me go to the Cruizer.
Let me tell the governor what I have done.
Let me look Mistress Fraser in the eye
one last time and confess.
On our wedding day, I swore to Claire
she'd have the protection of my name,
my clan, my family,
and the protection of my...
my body as well.
I will honor that promise.
I dinna need yer help.
I believe that in letting me go to her,
you will honor that promise just the same,
just as you've honored the promises made
to those of us who were at Ardsmuir.
I have no name
that carries any weight in this world.
A broken family.
No clan of my own.
Allow me to do this.
I can say nothin' to dissuade ye?
No.
Send Claire back to me.
That blackened day...
Mistress Fraser told us
what she would have said
about Malva at her funeral.
I won't have a eulogy,
and I don't know
what sort of burial awaits me.
But...
...I do wonder what you
might have said about me.
- Tom...
- Please.
I would say that Thomas Christie
was an honorable Scot...
...a leader of men
in his own way,
though he didna ken
quite where to lead them.
Stubborn as a damned mule...
...but despite our differences,
a man I respected
and whose respect I hope I had in return.
Boat, ahoy!
Jamie said he was coming back.
You will see him presently.
He awaits you in Wilmington.
What the hell is going on?
I've come to confess
to the murder of my daughter.
No.
No, you couldn't have.
Still contrary, I see.
- Are you insane?
- It's the truth.
I will swear to it by the Holy Scriptures.
I...
I don't understand.
Do you remember once,
you asked me if I thought you a witch?
You said you didn't think I was one.
No. But I have known them.
The girl was one. So was her mother.
"The girl" was your daughter, Malva.
No daughter of mine.
- Mr. Christie--
- She was my brother's.
Edgar.
When the Rising came, I...
declared for the Stuarts.
He would have none of it,
saying it was folly. He...
He begged me not to go.
I asked him to look after
my wife and wee Allan.
And he did.
He certainly did.
I see.
It wasn't his fault.
Mona was a witch,
an enchantress.
And he succumbed to her.
I see you don't believe me,
but it is the truth.
More than once, I caught her at it,
working her charms
and staring at the stars,
her hair flying loose, mad in the wind.
She had hair like mine, didn't she?
Leave it.
I tried to save her by prayer,
by God's grace.
I could not.
She was eventually hanged
for the murder of my brother.
So you sent for Allan and Malva.
By the time she came to me,
Malva already had it,
the same slyness, the charm,
the same darkness of soul as her mother.
I tried to keep her from
working her wiles upon men.
It was the curse of Lilith
that they had, both of them.
She was with child.
I do not think it wrong
to prevent yet another witch
from entering the world.
You know she tried to kill you?
You and me both.
You can't be certain of that.
It was you who told me that we suffered
with the same illness
during the flux at the Ridge.
You told her about the invisible things,
the--the germs.
She confessed when I caught her
with the Sin-Eater's bones.
She'd made a broth to poison us with.
Love charm.
She wanted Jamie.
She lusted after wealth, position.
Or what she saw as freedom.
Do you know who
the baby's father really was?
I could not let her destroy so many lives,
for she was a witch.
Make no mistake.
She would have killed someone
before she finished.
So you decided to bear that cross for her?
She was not born of my loins,
and yet she was my daughter,
my blood.
I am responsible.
I don't believe you, Tom.
I have waited all my life
in search of...
no, in hope of a thing
I could not name but I knew must exist.
I was convinced it was God I sought,
but the love of God alone
could not sustain me.
No.
Now I know
that I...
...I love you.
Here, now...
I have written down my confession.
I have sworn that I killed my daughter
for the shame she had brought
on me by her wantonness.
- No.
- I have written another copy
of this confession
and have already left it
with the newspaper in Wilmington.
They will publish it,
and you will go free.
I have yearned always for love,
given and returned.
I've spent my life
in the attempt to give my love
to those who are not worthy of it.
Allow me this...
...to give my life
for the sake of one who is.
Your life has value.
You can't throw it away like this.
I know that.
If I did not, then this would not matter.
Go to your husband.
There must be something we can do.
Lieutenant Tate...
I'm ready now.
Did you make Tom confess?
No.
No, he--he told me what he intended to do,
and I told him bide.
I did tell him that I'd have another go
at trying to get you back,
but he--he insisted.
So you don't think he did it either?
He only said he stayed silent
while there was any chance
of you bein' tried and acquitted,
but...
...had you ever been in any urgent danger,
he'd have spoken up at once.
That's why he insisted on
coming wi' us to Wilmington.
But that doesn't make any sense.
Why didn't he speak up in front of Brown?
I wondered if it was Brown
who killed Malva himself,
but... lookin' for revenge.
Maybe.
I just can't believe it was Tom.
Tell me he didn't make
that confession for me.
He loves you.
It's plain to see, Sassenach.
I'd have done the same,
counted my life well lost if it saved you.
But how can I let him
sacrifice himself for me?
They're going to hang him, Jamie.
If he feels the same as me,
then you've done no wrong to him
to take your life from his hand.
It's what he wanted.
Rest now, mo chridhe.
I saw your horse.
I'd know him anywhere.
Stared at his arse for 200 miles.
So...
you didn't fancy a trip
back to bonnie Scotland then,
eh, Mr. Fraser?
No.
No, thank ye.
I'd prefer to wait until after.
"After"?
Come now.
You harm a hair on my head,
you know my kin will hunt you down,
kill everyone you hold dear.
I've spared them the trouble.
By now, my nephew,
the Indian ye tormented,
will be payin' yer men a wee visit.
His Cherokee acquaintances
will be giving him
a helping hand too.
We'll have no more trouble from them.
You're a good man.
A moral man.
I'm also a violent man.
Any goodness that prevails in me
is because of my wife.
You tried to take her from me.
You won't kill me.
Not in cold blood.
You wouldn't dare.
Make your peace with the Lord
if you must...
Mr. Brown.